[SPEAKER_00]: I was reading that sutta of Arahant Talaputta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you remember it?
[SPEAKER_00]: With the...
[SPEAKER_01]: He was the... that comedian... comedian actor.
[SPEAKER_00]: That one with the... he's Arahant in his... that poem and he's saying
[SPEAKER_00]: How he wanted to live.
[SPEAKER_00]: When will I live in the forest?
[SPEAKER_00]: He's fantasizing, romanticizing about the mossy, mossy rocks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, when will I hear the peacock's cry?
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, when he was there, the mind wanted to go back to lay life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he says, now he won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he starts to say, when will I be a great monk?
[SPEAKER_00]: When will I be at peace?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, he starts to tell off his mind, ask the mind questions like, why didn't you urge me on before to become an ascetic, to go to the forest, and yet now, you want me to go after the things that you said I should be giving up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I've given them up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm not going to go and do those things which I vomited up.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not going to eat it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, he continues to berate the mind in such a way, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: And at the end, it starts to say, well, now I'm in control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I'm going to tie you down until you sort of get tamed, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's... that's... that is everyone's relationship with their own mind, usually... well, not usually, always.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only difference is how much perspective in regard to it you have, or how much you identify with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind presents you these ideas, and then you accept them, and then you act out of them, and then you kind of assume the ownership over them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you didn't really have say in their creation, in their arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind came up with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, oh yeah, I had these thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you realize, also, it's not about me coming up with it, or me owning or disowning that which is not in my control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Up to me is basically whether I choose to accept it, what the mind presented me with.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, whether you choose to accept what the eyes want to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eyes are pulling you in a direction,
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't have to accept it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to go with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if people have no self-awareness, no perspective developed through sense-restraint, for them, that pull is theirs.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ironically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, they're being pulled against their will, but they believe that's what they want to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, Talaputta, and that's what already had... had already some wisdom there, because he already was able to see a mind as this thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That, oh, yeah, you urged me to do this, I did this, now I want to go back.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he didn't have wisdom, he would have just thought, I want to go back.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he questioned, well, is this what I want?
[SPEAKER_01]: This is what my mind wants, it's clear enough, but is this what I want?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I don't want to eat what I vomited.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I was miserable over there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I left, to try this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I don't want to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the mind still wants it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's a conflict.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have a choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Give in to the mind, in order to not endure the conflict, or tame the mind, in order to resolve the conflict.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there will be no more conflict when you are in charge.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the... the mind offered him something good in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, exactly, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was... And obviously, that was due to, you know, his own pondering, reflection, choices.
[SPEAKER_01]: He did meet the Buddha as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then he thought, actually, even his own mind thought, this is worthwhile doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, even his own mind was not happy in that environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why I presented him with these romantic ideas of the forest and the jungle.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, when the, you know, the reality of those romantic ideas sets in, the hardship, enduring the elements of the insects, then the mind changes itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, actually, I want to...
[SPEAKER_01]: I changed my mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to go back.
[SPEAKER_01]: My mind has changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: He wants to go back, but shall I follow it?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like what we're saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start seeing yourself as this creature, the five, six sense animal,
[SPEAKER_01]: That senses will operate for as long as you live.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will want to pull you in direction they want to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's you to stop gratuitously identifying with them and giving in to their pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they'll obey, eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: How long that will take is how much effort you put in.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the chief is the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the animal which really needs to be...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind directs all the other animals and the mind is basically that which is the hardest to tame.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you recognize you have such and such thoughts, but then you reflect further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, the mind... Like, when the mind is sort of interested in sensuality, for example, the mind will not think about the ugly aspects that are simultaneously there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can make it do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what he decided to do there.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I will tie you down, this mind, and I'll stay where you told me to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: I accept that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was a good idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, we're not changing this.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're gonna stay here until you listen to me, not other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not about not having those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about preventing them from arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: I shouldn't be thinking this.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not up to you what you think.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's up to your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you should not be acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Acting upon it and accepting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without further consideration.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know exactly where the line is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is not my responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind can come with whatever it wants.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I will not entertain it, encourage it, if it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's up to you to choose.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's up to you to choose to accept the offer of the mind or not, to go with it, along with it, to act upon it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, it's also... it's up to you to choose whether to... to allow mind to... to keep dwelling and revolve.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it needs your input, it needs your encouragement to keep revolving around, say, centrality or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you should develop the perception of danger in those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, while the mind is thinking those thoughts of centrality, you are not wanting them because they are dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, I will have mind never think that again.
[SPEAKER_01]: That might be the final outcome of you being completely dispassionate towards what your mind presents you with.
[SPEAKER_01]: But until then, the mind will be presenting you with stuff, same as any other sense will be presenting you for what it wants to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you must not welcome it, if you know it, if you see that it's rooted in sensuality, your will, or distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean, I don't want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let this... let make these thoughts go away.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it means, I don't want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now I have to endure this unruly mind that is trying to harass me with these thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were saying the other day about... there is a sutra on that... that greed is mildly blameworthy and slow to fade.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hatred is very blameworthy, quick to fade.
[SPEAKER_00]: Delusion is very blameworthy and slow to fade.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, delusion is the worst.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the subtlest.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the most... well, it's the most primordial out of three, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the practice, if you want to practice getting rid of delusion... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I think what the most, or certainly fairly important thing, is to make sure that it's not misunderstood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, people, like, lust is obvious, greed is obvious, well, obvious, obviously on the level of idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, people, you know, when you say greed, people know, okay, that's greed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you say delusion, I think more often than not, people would would think of it as as, like, some sort of confusion, ignorance of something you don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're deluded, in some, almost like a metaphysical sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when you become enlightened now, you penetrate it through the delusion and, you know, the secrets have been revealed and there is no more delusion in you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not something, some piece of information that you don't have.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's existential attitude that you have towards your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Towards the sense organs, the delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I often say delusion slash distraction, because it's an active thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not, oh, yeah, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's somewhere there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm working through these methods and techniques and I'm reading the suttas and, you know, somehow I'm affecting this accumulated delusion at the back of my mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Delusion is something you do here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, greed is something you would be doing here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or be liable to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And anger is something you will be doing here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's on the same practical basis of something that you welcome, and act upon, and accept, and don't see for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like something you don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically something that you keep doing, that is mistaken.
[SPEAKER_01]: Towards the senses, towards engagement with the world...
[SPEAKER_00]: The attitude of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the attitude of, basically, the attitude of distraction, it's about that, the movement of distraction, the movement of having something to do, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: A good indicator, as we spoke before, would be to measure it with boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are easily, if somebody who is easily bored, means you have accumulated a lot of delusion, they will be hard to see and hard to fade.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you never get bored, well, you're probably at least anāgāmī or maybe an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no pressure of non-activity at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: No pressure to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: No pressure to look away or distract yourself from nothing happening, nothing being felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, practically speaking, boredom is a good way to practice as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And often, you know, like, keeping the precepts from your life, that's what's going to result into.
[SPEAKER_01]: But see, then you have the problem of people don't see boredom as an indicator, and they certainly don't see a delusion as an attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: They still cultivate, despite their commitment to precepts, and commitment to suttas, and commitment to meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, they always try to deal with boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even when they're practicing, your meditation technique becomes something you do on account of avoiding boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your reading the suttas, studies, scholarly work, becomes something you do on account of avoiding boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, you need to know the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to collect this information in order to know what to look for.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, sooner or later, you need to start uprooting delusion for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for that, you need to endure and not depend always on some activity to keep you occupied and engaged and basically connected to the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, you decide to get bored.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, switch your phone off, no interest in anything, close your doors, pull the shutters.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter whether you sit, stand, walk around your apartment.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will not obviously watch anything, read anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will not do your meditation technique and watch your nostrils and perform these methods of doing for an hour.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just going to abide in non-activity, as the suttas would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the mind will be presenting you, do this, do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't try to get rid of those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just don't act on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, oh, I'll get up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I can get up.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not an activity of a kind that would distract you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll go to toilet.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not an activity of a kind to distract you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, let me just check my... oh, that's an activity of a kind, so I will not do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You probably do that for an hour, you're gonna feel intense boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why people fear that solitude, confinement, when there is nothing to distract their senses and give that impending sort of prospect of doing something, completing something, finding something, seeing something, hearing something, resolving, performing something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's frightening.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in itself...
[SPEAKER_01]: Being something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: In itself, that's not frightening.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's only frightening because you've been depending on the momentum of action always.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's gratuitous dependence that you've been cultivating because you didn't know any better.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for as long as you don't know any better, you will be cultivating.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, so that's when we... Are you delighting in projects?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you delighting in work?
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you are delighting in distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's also, like, where your practice of samādhi can be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just try and abide in true non-activity for an hour or two.
[SPEAKER_01]: No meditation techniques, no trying to be mindful, performing mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just sit there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't fall asleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: Get up if you're sleepy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stand or walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, just allow your mind to keep coming up with these ideas, what to do, planning, and then don't commit to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just let them endure there and sit about.
[SPEAKER_01]: And do that for three or four hours, and you see, basically, there's going to be space created, unwittingly for most people, initially, between you and your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that identification that I mentioned in the beginning, that people naturally jump into with the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense wants to see, I want to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense wants to hear, I want to hear.
[SPEAKER_01]: That needs maintenance of that proximity, of that closeness, of that immediate acting upon impulse.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't act upon impulse,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're restrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, even your thoughts of, hey, look at this, do that, plan that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, let that endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not, I'm not accepting that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll probably do it later.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing unwholesome with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, I'm concerned about non-activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will create that space because you're not now jumping upon every impulse of your sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you get to actually see the creature for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind there, like, with thoughts, want to do this, want to do that, the monkey mind, the, you know, all the eyes, all these animal comparisons to the senses, you get to see it, because you stop being kind of driven by them, like, on a closed leash.
[SPEAKER_01]: You actually stepped away.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, even if you choose to do something, say, if you establish now that, if that's your practice for most of the day, abiding in non-activity,
[SPEAKER_01]: Wakeful, because you're not sleeping, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, just... just seeing where your mind comes up, it endures the next thing, the next thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, when you do commit to do something with your body, with your mouth, with your speech, with your mind, you do so only on the level of that kind of recognition that this will not cause further distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, those things that you do, you do them through the mind of non-activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why in jhāna, you can, you know, walk, eat, go to toilet, you know, patch your robe, do stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like you're frozen, motionless, because it's non-activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's meant by non-activity means non... non... no activity that's rooted in distraction, that it's motivated by that fundamental delusion to distract yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's that's the measure there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it will also become clear what you are not distracting yourself from.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: These creatures of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why people fear boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I'm bored.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stay bored a bit longer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I'm afraid now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, boredom will always turn into anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you start seeing your existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you start seeing how basically divorced from your own senses you are, from things that you identify with, that defines what you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just like, as I said, it's like, you know, like somebody releases a helium balloon that just starts, you know, untethered, just goes higher and higher and higher and higher.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your mind now, because there is no end to how high it can go.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no problem in how high it goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is from your expectation and need and dependence of being tethered to the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you haven't been restraining yourself enough, you haven't been seeing the danger in the slightest fall.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have been depending on action of your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, that's why, like, you have many, you know, you met in your life, everybody, have met people in life, who have, who always depend on having something to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody depends on having something to do, but some people more than others.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when they constantly need to be active, if they're not active, haha, I'm bored, and then restlessness set in, and then anxiety, and everything, doesn't matter how insignificant, becomes the most important thing in the world that must be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you're dying, you're barely moving, you're 90 years old, but your whole life has been depending on having something to do, and you will still be trying to do stuff, because otherwise it's just too frightening, too overwhelming.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, that is only because you refuse to give up the gratuitous assumptions that these senses are yours, are worth holding on to, are the basis for identification.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you give that up, then the loftiness of non-activity, the expanse, the immeasurability of the non-active mind, mind withdrawn from dependence on the sense activity, is the most sublime thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as we described before, the pleasure of jhāna, the pleasure of the neutral feeling, needs to be understood, needs to be learned, needs to be developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not automatic.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, by the way, that's why, like, say, you haven't had anything to do for five hours, you were confined in a room, and then now you're released, and it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the most
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the dirtiest of the chores.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to go and clean the toilet.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will enjoy it, because at least, at least, there's something for you to do, if you're still dependent on the action.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize now, the pleasure of having something to do is determined from how far your mind has went away, how far has it withdrawn.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you see, people who never experience boredom, because they always have something lined up to do and distract themselves with,
[SPEAKER_01]: There are people who then double down even more onto sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing, by the way, there's nothing sensual with cleaning the toilet.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you just enjoy the action in itself, because the boredom was a bit too much to handle.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, say, you never really experience boredom, you never experience any separation from the senses, like stepping back, no perspective in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you do is engage with the senses, that's when you now need even more engagement for any sense of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the more you engage with sensuality, the less pleasure you feel, the more you need to engage.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, say, you've been withdrawn from sensuality for a long time, even a little bit of engagement with the sense will be very agreeable and pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't constitute sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Engagement with the sense in itself doesn't constitute sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: The further now you have distracted yourself, you use the engagement with the senses basically for the basis of your own self-delusion from yourself, now you seek the further pleasure of the sense objects, that's where your sensuality sets in.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the Buddha described the difference between pleasure that is underlied by more craving, by lust for more pleasure, and pleasure that isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, pleasure of cleaning a toilet is not underlined for more pleasure to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually determined by the fact that you haven't been engaging with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't need to fear that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you need to be careful though, because you will then be trying to find out random things to do, because they are not sensual, but they can become distracting.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if they do, then your mind will start thinking sensual thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: It goes in that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Goes further in that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the same principle, taken even further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, say you don't fear the boredom anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't fear the neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not felt unpleasantly, because you understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You basically live withdrawn from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have developed the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your mind is now even more established upon the greater separation from the senses and sense pools and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why then, from that perspective, even enduring discomfort will be felt like divine pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from the point of view of boredom, cleaning the toilet will be felt extremely exhilarating.
[SPEAKER_01]: From the point of view of jhāna, physical endurance of torture, rough robes, bare food and medicine, living under the root of a tree, will be felt absolutely like the finest robes, the finest food, the finest medicine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Determined by how much your mind is withdrawn, that determines how pleasant the engagement will be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why for some people, like the whole world of sensuality, whatever they want, they feel numb.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they've been engaging with that level of senses for so long.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind is not withdrawn.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the same principle of withdrawal.
[SPEAKER_01]: In boredom, if you work through the boredom, don't act out of it, endure it, even endure that anxiety if it arises, then even chores will be seen as agreeable, as fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will still not lose, unless you choose to, you will not lose that recognition that, oh, the non-activity,
[SPEAKER_01]: State of mind that has arisen on account of enduring boredom and not acting upon the sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, because of that, I have pleasant abiding here and now, when I do have to engage with the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you develop that further into a jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, even if you don't do any chores, just enduring the elements will be agreeable, will be seen pleasantly, from the point of view of mind so withdrawn.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what I would encourage Venerable Anuruddin.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Practice jhāna, so that the rough robes you wear will feel like silk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of the mind of jhāna, mind of withdrawal from the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, but, so, me enjoying these rough robes, oh, that's sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... Only a person who is not free from sensuality would use that as a ref... and think that everything is sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the only reference you have.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even the Buddha himself initially thought that pleasure of that withdrawal
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unwholesome, but then says, wait, why do I fear this pleasure that is not connected with that double down pleasure of sense objects, that you have to be craving for more if you engage with?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always underlied by more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is not underlined.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why do I fear it?
[SPEAKER_01]: What if I don't fear it?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, he realized it shouldn't be feared.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're enjoying the living in the in the in the jungle, wearing the rough robes and enduring insects, if you find that's agreeable, you don't need to have that centrality, because it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: That agreeability of it is determined by your state of loftiness of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not distracting yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will inevitably find things enjoyable.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you develop jhānas, as they did in the suttas, even like the extreme physical rotting guts and stuff, like, no, it's alright, I'll endure this, no problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because my mind can obtain jhānas at will.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, my mind can re-establish itself as fully withdrawn and independent of any sense at will.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can I be bothered by anything that comes through any sense?
[SPEAKER_01]: When Mahākassapa was offered by the Buddha, because he was already old, to leave the rough forest, stop living, keeping all those dūtanga, ascetic practices, because it's it's too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said, you did your work.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's really no need for this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Come on.
[SPEAKER_01]: I get plenty of robes, plenty of food, plenty of lodging.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll pass it down onto you.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's really no need for you to torture yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, oh, no, Lord, this is not a torture.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whoever can obtain jhānas at will, this is what they want to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is where their joy is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they will say, oh, you're truly practicing for the sake of future generation.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, that's the inspiring thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no further dhamma to be developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: You completed everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now you do it for the sake of pleasure and joy that you find in it, because you can obtain jhānas at will.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he, you know, there were no records of him how he died, but he must have died in the same environment.
[SPEAKER_01]: He never left the hardship and ascetic practices, because they were not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The relativity of hardship and endurance is determined by how much your mind is withdrawn from these things or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is... that's why it's not incidental that boredom is always that fundamental thing that nobody wants to deal with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even people that practice the dhamma, the practice of dhamma, because something you do to avoid that sinking into that boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, say you've been sitting for three hours, closed in your room, everything switched off, no notifications, no activity, and you want to get up and drink tea.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now your mind starts... wants to overthink it, wants to get into details.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what you don't welcome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't mean I will never drink tea again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you see the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will not lose the sight of yourself, which means even making of the tea will not become a basis for that self-deluding, whereby you become unaware of yourself and you fall into the identification of the senses you're engaging with.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still maintain that distance, the right perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are living in such a way, non-distraction, doing things not to distract yourself, your life becomes simple.
[SPEAKER_00]: Naturally, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Naturally results in simplicity.
[SPEAKER_01]: The amount of proliferation and elaboration towards the senses and engagement with it, yeah, that will have to diminish.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would fail.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why working, talking and sleeping, not sensual in itself,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the one with the right view, who, if he were to practice sense restraint and learn to abide in non-activity even more, will become an arahant in this life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, they get distracted with work, talk and sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: That becomes basically obstruction to their own progress.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the Buddha would tell off Ananda and other, you know, Aryas.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were, like, busy sewing robes and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was obviously not necessary to the extent that they were doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha really rebuked them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not sensual.
[SPEAKER_01]: Enjoying work is not sensual.
[SPEAKER_01]: Enjoying talk is not sensual.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless, obviously, the talk is about sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you lose the context, and if you don't maintain that transparency in regard to the motivation behind engagement with work, talk and sleep, it will become a basis for maintaining... Obviously, for, you know, for an ārya, he maintains that delusion much subtler than a puṭṭhujana would be doing, but it's still a form of that self-destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all he would need to do is not engage, or not allow himself to be engaged with work for the purpose of distraction, talk for the purpose of distraction, and sleep for the purpose of distraction, and he will progress towards nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: No other effort he needs to make.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he already understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: The effort of non-activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the effort of protecting the mind of non-activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all in the suttas what you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Abide in non-activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a pleasant abiding here and now, paired with your right view, is basically jhāna that leads you to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said many times, jhāna is not a product of your activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jhāna is the product of withdrawal from the senses, pleasure and security that comes from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the true non-activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, non-activity is basically whether you are motivated by distraction or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not whether you are motionless or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might just jump into the conclusion, ah, non-activity means motionless for three hours, I will refuse to move because there will be a distraction of activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-activity means non-distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, are you abiding in non-distraction?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know that, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just, as I said, just sit in a flat,
[SPEAKER_01]: And see, within five minutes, the mind will present you something to do, and you will catch yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you relishing the idea of, yes, let me do this, let me click that button, let me open that door, let me look at this.
[SPEAKER_01]: If so, there you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not acting upon an impulse to act, it's already creating some space between you and your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why none of this would be possible unless you keep the precepts beforehand and practice and restrain your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-activities, not being motivated and not using any type of action for the means of distraction of yourself from yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not use any type of action for the basis for identification with the senses, for losing the perspective of the creature that needs to be contained and restrained and kept an eye on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's nothing like the decrease of delusion and the right perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're keeping that perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: The increase of that...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start giving in to these distracting activities, the perspective, the right perspective, will diminish or will be more obscured.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't give in to these acts of self-distraction, the perspective is maintained.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't need to...
[SPEAKER_01]: I must keep this perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: All I need to do is protect it by not distracting myself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's that indirect...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you stop being engaged with the world, like with work or whatever else you have to do, now you realize, oh, there is enough space for me here to see if the actions I'm about to do and what I'm doing when I'm not working, do I need to, and to what extent I'm using that for basically pleasure of... of kind of indolence and forgetting about this creature that I do need to keep an eye on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need, as I said before, you don't need to be choking creature and constantly tying it up, but you do need to not lose the sight of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now that you finished your work, when you come back at home, you need to rest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does that include binge-watching, I don't know, a four-hour long movie, having a drink, listening to the music?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where does it... where does it say that you need to do that for relaxation?
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do for relaxation is not do any work.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you realize, okay, yeah, so I can easily relax myself and enjoy doing nothing, or enjoy doing something that's non-distracting, and that will not result in me wanting to do more of it and losing the sight of myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, I could then...
[SPEAKER_01]: Also, choose to do things that would result in such things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, watching entertainment, engagement with chit-chat, people, company.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that will take you away even further from the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, although it's not technically still central, it's already heading in that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Direction of depending on activity and work and so on, which means it's just a question of time when you're going to be seeking the central objects and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to relax, but not to the point of losing the sight of the creature you need to keep an eye on, that you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: And often people conflate the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've done my work, now I can relax, means I can lose the sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, you can relax, but at no point that means you are allowed to lose the sight of the creature of the six senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... that's a no-no.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's that difference between activity and non-activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't lose the sight of the creature, you will not be active on the level of the creature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're doing the chores, you will be doing them through the mind of non-activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only to the minimum point of complete the need, the purpose, and then you're back into non-activity and abiding in jhāna, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with like eating, if you were to eat...
[SPEAKER_01]: Same with eating, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: To the extent that needs to be eaten, then finished, then not seen as even pleasurable to do more.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is pleasurable is protecting the mind that makes everything else pleasurable, from that high stance.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize, oh, that's the true pleasure, that's the pleasure that's not underlined by craving for more, and that pleasure is not unwholesome, it's safe, and you're mindful in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a win-win.